Guide to the New-York Historical Society Management Committee Records 1804-1938 NYHS-RG 1
New-York Historical Society
- Series II. Executive Committee Minutes, 1843-1938; 2.4 Linear feet
  The keyword "building" is used when the general physical plant is concerned, such as with renovations, maintenance/repairs, or rentals or other outside use of the facility. Outside organizations would commonly request permission for use of the "hall" and that keyword is typically used in that context. In the 1890s-early 1900s when N-YHS was based in its longstanding Second Avenue site while purchasing, maintaining, then constructing at its present Central Park West site, the keywords distinguishing the two sites are "Second Avenue" and "Central Park West site."
  "Acquisition" is used as a keyword for potential or actual additions to the collections. "Donation" (rather than "gift" or "presented") and "purchase" are also used as keywords with acquisition ("acquisition by donation") when known. The word "deposit" and/or "custody" was used as a keyword, rather than "acquisition," when the minutes use that term. "Bequest" is used as a keyword instead of legacy or inheritance. Cash donations for general or specific purposes tend to use the keyword "subscriptions" in the first several volumes and "contributions" thereafter.
  "Financial matters" refers most commonly to expense payments, which are listed for approval by the committee in the volumes. These expenses include staff compensation, printing, advertising, rent, coal, repairs, furnishings and supplies, meeting refreshments, collection conservation, etc. Payment for "strawberries" appears from time to time on the early bill lists and these were noted with that keyword. Payments made to specific staff for salary and/or services rendered are included in these expense lists. The at times controversial history of N-YHS's compensation to its Librarian, essentially the chief operating officer of the organization into the mid-20th century, can be traced through these bill lists. "Financial matters" also brings results for general financial issues, such as the financial state of the organization.
  Beginning in early 1883 (Volume RG1.16), regular reporting of the bank balances of the general account and various special purpose restricted funds were reported and recorded in the minutes; accordingly, beginning with RG1.16, in addition to the keyword "financial matters," the terms "expense payments" and "bank balances" are used to facilitate more targeted searching. By the late 1800s, specific funds were used for particular purposes (e.g., Phoenix Fund for collection purchases, sometimes listed out specifically; Building Fund for the Central Park West site development) and those fund names were used as keywords. "Investments" is used for the investment of N-YHS funds in securities, mortgage loans and other vehicles.
  "Routine business" is used extensively. For a typical committee meeting, this term refers to the approval of minutes, scheduling of meetings of the committee or of the Society, naming new subcommittee members, assigning routine tasks to ad hoc committees or officers, extending invitations to dignitaries or others to attend Society meetings, accepting officer or committee resignations and preparing related acknowledgements of them for the minutes, etc. One routine task was the charge to draft memorials on the occasion of a member's death; "obituary" is used where the minutes include the substantive, often biographical, wording of such a memorial, and "memorial" is used for briefer acknowledgements of a paragraph or two. "Routine business" also applies to the administrative actions taken at the committee's annual reorganization meetings, which took place in mid-late January just after the N-YHS annual business meeting. At the mid-January committee meeting, the names of the Executive Committee members for the year were recorded, subcommittees established, committee officers named, annual reports were ordered to be published, and so forth.
  - Executive Committee Minutes. April 1843-May [June] 1852, 1843-1852 (Volume RG1.11)
    On-line Access to Digital Copy
    This volume is available on-line via this link.
  - Exec Committee Minutes. September 1852-January 7, 1862, 1852-1862 (Volume RG1.12)
  - Exec Committee Minutes. January 28, 1862-September 1866, 1862-1866 (Volume RG1.13)
  - Executive Committee Minutes. October 1866-January 1873, 1866-1873 (Volume RG1.14)
  - Exec Committee Minutes. February 1873-December 1879, 1873-1879 (Volume RG1.15)
  - Exec Committee Minutes. 1880-1884 (Volume RG1.16)
  - Exec Committee Minutes. January 1885-October 7, 1890, 1885-1890 (Volume RG1.17)
  - Exec Committee Minutes. October 21, 1890-March 1900, 1890-1900 (Volume RG1.18)
  - Exec Committee Minutes. April 1900-October 1904, 1900-1904 (Volume RG1.19)
  - Exec Committee Minutes. November 1904-June 1907, 1904-1907 (Volume RG1.20)
  - Exec Committee Minutes. October 1907-April 1910, 1907-1910 (Volume RG1.21)
    This volume is available on-line via this link
  - Exec Committee Minutes. May 1910-January 1913, 1910-1913 (Volume RG1.22)
  - Exec Committee Minutes. February 1913-December 1915, 1913-1915 (Volume RG1.23)
  - Exec Committee Minutes. January 1916-February 1918, 1916-1918 (Volume RG1.24)
  - Exec Committee Minutes. March 1918-January [February] 1921, 1918-1921 (Volume RG1.25)
  - Loose Document Removed from Exec Committee Minutes (Volume RG1.25 ), 1920 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes list of Standing Committees and committee members for 1920.
  - Exec Committee Minutes. March 15, 1921-March 18, 1924, 1921-1924 (Volume RG1.26)
  - Exec Committee Minutes. April 15, 1924-November 15, 1927, 1924-1927 (Volume RG1.27)
  - Loose Documents Removed from Exec Committee Minutes (Volume RG1.27), 1921-1926 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes lists of dues in arrears and a printed version of N-YHS's acknowledgement to the Naval History Society accepting its collection (1925).
  - Exec Committee Minutes. December 20, 1927-December 15, 1931, 1927-1931 (Volume RG1.28)
  - Loose Documents Removed from Exec Committee Minutes (Volume RG1.28), 1928, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Includes an unsigned bank resolution related to the Thompson bequest (1928); a list of Standing Committees and committee members (1930); and two sample title pages for the Edwin Smith surgical papyrus publication.
  - Exec Committee Minutes. January 19, 1932-May 19, 1936, 1932-1936 (Volume RG1.29)
  - Exec Committee Minutes. June 1936-December 1938, 1936-1938 (Volume RG1.30)
    In addition to the minutes of the final meetings of the Executive Committee, this volume holds the December 1937-1938 minutes of the newly-constituted Board of Trustees.
- Series III. Other Committee Minutes, 1806-1822, 1856-1880; 0.4 Linear feet
  The Other Committee Minutes series includes the following three volumes:
  The first volume holds minutes recorded by the Standing Committee and lists of early donations to N-YHS. The Standing Committee existed from 1805 until 1829 when the requirement for it was removed from the N-YHS Constitution and By-Laws. The volume does not include records from this entire period. Only four meetings of the Standing Committee are recorded; one of these (1807) was adjourned for lack of a quorum and the other three (1806, 1809, 1810) include only a small number of committee resolutions, one of which concerns the possible purchase of items from John Pintard. The bulk of the entries in the volume are lists of donations of books and other objects (1806 to 1818, with gaps, and 1822); these entries often, though not always, also indicate the donor.
  The second volume holds minutes of the Mineralogical Committee, dating from 1818-1819. Although the committee was formed in October 1816 and existed until perhaps circa 1920 (the Society meeting minutes are silent on when the committee was discharged), this slender volume holds the brief minutes for only two meetings: December 28, 1818, and March 6, 1819. The minutes also include a letter from the committee's secretary indicating his unavailability for a March 26, 1819 meeting.
  The third volume holds minutes of the Committee on Fine Arts, dating from its formation in March 1856 to March 1880. Although the committee existed until May 1895, there are no entries after March 1880. The minutes refer to the committee's support for collecting photographs, consideration of the Jarvis collection, the Audubon watercolors, the Bryan collection, the possibility of acquiring space for N-YHS in Central Park, and Mathew Brady's offer of photographs to N-YHS, among other matters.
  The three volumes are listed here chronologically by their earliest entry. Within each volume, the entries proceed chronologically.
  The bound pages of the Mineralogical Committee volume include only the December 1818 meeting minutes. The other content is on two loose sheets that were inserted into the volume. These two sheets were removed to a separate folder, which is noted in the container list below.
  The Standing Committee and Fine Arts Committee volumes were bound in new covers in July 1936 by the New-York Historical Society. The Mineralogical Committee volume is in its original binding and covers.
  A photocopy of the Standing Committee book is available for general access use. The photocopy is complete as to the book's bound pages, but does not include two loose sheets that are with the committee book. It also cuts off a small amount of information and is difficult to read at points because of the poor reproduction quality. Accordingly the photocopy cannot be relied on as a replacement for the original, but it is preferable to use over the somewhat fragile original for users initially surveying the document for potential usefulness.
  - Standing Committee and Record of Donations (1 of 2), 1806-1818, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Standing Committee and Record of Donations (2 of 2), 1806-1818, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    This folder includes a photocopy of the Standing Committee book that is available for general access use. The photocopy is complete as to the original's bound pages, but does not include copies of two loose sheets that are with the committee book. It also cuts off a small amount of information and is difficult to read at points because of the poor reproduction quality. Accordingly the photocopy cannot be relied on as a replacement for the original, but it is preferable to use over the somewhat fragile original for users initially surveying the document for potential usefulness.
  - Mineralogical Committee, 1818-1819 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Committee on Fine Arts, 1856-1880 (Volume RG1.31, Folder -)
- Series IV. Official Papers, 1805-1938; 10.6 Linear feet
  The Official Papers series, which is the original name of the files, primarily includes material that directly relates to the Society membership and Executive Committee meetings and minute books (see Series I and II). Most of the documents are preparatory material for the meetings, preliminary notes and drafts of meeting minutes, or supporting or source materials concerning matters presented at the meetings. Much of the material in this series is likely also found recorded in the minute books or in print form, but that may not be true in all instances and these documents are typically the draft or manuscript versions which can have a research value separate from the final versions.
  For each year's files from the 1840s to the 1910s, the overall content is fairly consistent. The files for these years primarily include documentation of proposed new members; drafts or manuscripts of the Librarian and Executive Committee's annual reports; drafts of statements and resolutions, including memorial remarks for recently deceased members; and documentation of the annual nomination and election of officers. The membership documentation is especially extensive and includes the original correspondence, paper slips, business cards, or standardized forms nominating candidates as members; the extract from the minutes recording the nominations, which were forwarded to the Executive Committee for its consideration; and the communication from the committee recommending acceptance of the nominees.
  Also commonly found in the files of the 1840s to 1910s, though less consistently than the above materials, are remarks made by newly-elected presidents, reports of various committees formed on an ad hoc basis for particular purposes, and some financial and donation information. Some legal documents are in the series, including the agreement by which N-YHS acquired the collection of the New York Gallery of Fine Arts. Documentation related to the funding and construction of buildings for N-YHS is found in the years 1840s-1850s, and again in the 1880s-early 1900s. References to the publications program and its funding and to various special events are found here also. The container list below includes notes at the folder level to highlight at least some of the noteworthy items identified during processing.
  The series includes a set of files dating from 1899-1905 that were maintained by Sydney H. Carney, Jr., N-YHS's Recording Secretary for much of this period. Carney was also a member of the Central Park West Building Committee during this period and was that committee's secretary in some years. The most substantive portions of Carney's files relate to the building project, especially in regard to controversy over the architect's unanticipated need to change the building design. These documents include correspondence from architects York & Sawyer and others; draft resolutions; drafts of Carney's outgoing correspondence to the architects, to N-YHS presidents Eugene and Samuel Hoffman, and to others; notes taken about telephone calls; draft committee minutes; a subscription book; and other documents related to the project. Carney's files also include correspondence related to his Recording Secretary responsibilities, including requests from Librarian Robert H. Kelby for signatures on meeting extracts, member certificates, and Publication Fund shares and share transfers; requests for resolutions to be drafted; notices from officers and committee members of meetings they would be unable to attend; and other such routine business matters.
  Subsequent to the 1910s, for the files of the 1920s and 1930s, the scope of the documentation narrows, with little material related to the monthly Executive Committee minutes. Much of the routine matter for these years includes the manuscript Annual Reports (Librarian, Executive Committee, and Field Exploration Committee) and lists of approved new members and of deaths ("necrology"). The bulk of the documents for these years relate to the triennial officer elections, the by-law changes of 1917 and 1937, and the special membership meeting called in 1936 to approve the Executive Committee's decision to initiate construction of the Central Park West building expansion. Proxy voting was introduced with the 1917 elections and much of the bulk of the material for the 1920s and 1930s includes the proxy certificates and the recordkeeping concerning them. Nonetheless, the contentious elections of 1917 and 1920, driven by charges of mismanagement by Mrs. Van Rensselaer, are well-documented here with correspondence, circulars, meeting transcripts, and competing ballots.
  For consistency with the Executive Committee minutes series, the Official Papers series includes the year 1938, the first year that N-YHS was governed by a Board of Trustees, newly-constituted under the by-law changes of 1937.
  The earliest files in this series, from prior to the 1840s, are much more uneven in content and are of a different character than the later files. The bulk of the documents for these first three decades of N-YHS's history are invoices, receipts, and account statements, such as those related to purchases of books, moving the library to and setting up the rooms at the New York Institution and other places, creating the mineralogy cabinet, printing circulars and publishing advertisements, and other expenses. Files in the late 1820s are especially rich with regard to N-YHS's efforts to resolve its debts. This material concerns the claims of John Pintard and John Francis for purchases they made for N-YHS, and the releases obtained from various creditors. Other than financial matters, the early files contain some of N-YHS's early circulars to the public, meeting agendas and extracts, and librarian and committee reports.
  The series is arranged in chronological order, which appears to have been the original order of the files. The files advance in yearly increments, except for the files from N-YHS's earliest decades, which were somewhat disorganized and included multiple years.
  Within each year, the documents are also generally arranged in chronological order. Many documents though are undated; these were typically left in the folders in which they were found on the assumption they were filed with the correct year. These undated documents are found at the end of each year.
  Most years include the manuscript drafts of the annual reports of the Executive Committee and the Librarian. These reports were prepared for the January membership meeting and summarized the activities of the prior year. The original filing of these reports was inconsistent across the series and could not be reliably rationalized during processing, especially since some are undated and unclear as to which year they refer. Accordingly, the annual report drafts were left in the files in which they were found. For the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, a year's report will typically be found in the following year's file. From about 1920 through the end of the series in 1938, the report will be found with its subject year.
  Much of the material in the earliest years (1805-circa 1850) are invoices and other financial documents. Payment delays were common so the bills for a prior year are often found in the following year. Also, many of these financial documents are account statements that refer to past transactions of prior years.
  Folders labeled with just a date or date range include standard subject matter as described in the Scope and Contents Note. Some individual documents were identified as specifically noteworthy and were referenced in a note at the folder level. Folders that include a subject in their label include documents related to that subject only.
  Related Archival Materials Note
  While there is a fairly clear distinction between the two, there does seem to be instances in which documents that could be considered official papers were placed by N-YHS officers in the General Correspondence Files (NYHS-RG 2), and vice versa, particularly for the nineteenth century records. For example, correspondence read to the Society or a committee and "laid upon the table" or acted on, or a resignation letter by an officer, is more likely to be with correspondence than the official papers. Although some of these documents were moved between the official papers and correspondence during processing, for the most part items were left as found, and researchers may wish to check both record groups for a given year.
  - Official Papers. 1805-1813 (1 of 7). Constitution, Address and Queries (drafts). (Box 1, Folder 12)
    One of the drafts of the N-YHS Constitution indicates that it was found among family papers and presented to N-YHS by Samuel W. Francis, April 21, 1883.
  - Official Papers. 1805-1813 (2 of 7). Address to the Public (print)., 1805?, 1809-1810 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Official Papers. 1805-1813 (3 of 7). Membership Invitation with Constitution, Address and Queries (print)., 1805 February 12 (Box OS-1, Folder 8)
    Includes a print invitation to become a member of N-YHS, signed by Corresponding Secretary Samuel Miller.
  - Official Papers. 1805-1813 (4 of 7). New York Herald Publication of N-YHS Constitution, 1805 February 13 (Box OS-1, Folder 9)
  - Official Papers. 1805-1813 (5 of 7). Subscribers to the Anniversary Festival on St. Nicholas' Day, 1811 December (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Official Papers. 1805-1813 (6 of 7). Report of Librarian John W. Francis., 1812 December 7 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Official Papers. 1805-1813 (7 of 7). Donation List., 1813 July 21 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Official Papers. 1816 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Includes only one document: an extract of a letter from John W. Francis, writing from London with favorable views of Americans, the extract laid before a meeting of the Society.
  - Official Papers. 1817-1818 (1 of 3)., February-June 1817 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Includes the printed circular of the American Zoology and Geology Committee and the printed Report on Botany and Vegetable Physiology.
  - Official Papers. 1817-1818 (2 of 3)., October 1817-January 1818 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Official Papers. 1817-1818 (3 of 3)., April-December 1818 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Includes G. Schulte's manuscript on serpents that was presented by Gov. Clinton at the November 10, 1818, Society meeting and referred to the Committee on Publications. Includes a report on the development of the zoological and geological specimens in the Cabinet and reports about the Library.
  - Official Papers. 1819 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Includes a list of members from N-YHS's founding to October 1819; the list includes election date and the name of the nominating member. According to a card with the document, the list is in the handwriting of Dr. Lyman Spalding, N-YHS Corresponding Secretary in 1819-20. The list was given to N-YHS by Spalding's grandson, Dr. James Alfred Spalding, in 1919.
  - Official Papers. 1805-1819 (1 of 3). Invoices and Other Financial Documents., 1805, 1809-1811, 1816 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    See also the folders below for 1828; these include bills from 1809-19 submitted in 1828 by John Pintard for reimbursement. The bills include expenses related to the 1817 creation of the mineralogy cabinet.
  - Official Papers. 1805-1819 (2 of 3). Invoices and Other Financial Documents., 1817 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Official Papers. 1805-1819 (3 of 3). Invoices and Other Financial Documents., 1818-1819 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Includes invoice for cartage fees for a specimen of the Giant's Causeway.
  - Official Papers. "Invoices for Books, etc. Purchased for N-YHS by John W. Francis, John Pintard, and others" (1 of 2)., 1805, 1810, 1813-14, 1817-1818 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    These two folders of invoices include a note indicating they were presented to N-YHS by Dr. Valentine Matt Francis on Dec. 20, 1906.
  - Official Papers. "Invoices for Books, etc. Purchased for N-YHS by John W. Francis, John Pintard, and others" (2 of 2)., 1818, ca. 1818 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Official Papers. John W. Francis Documents, 1815, 1818, Undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Includes three photoreproductions of financial documents related to John Francis's transactions (originals not found).
  - Official Papers. Circa 1804-1820? (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Includes two undated documents: a draft of a "prospectus of a reading society" and a list of U.S. government documents of the 1790s.
  - Official Papers. 1820-1823 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Includes documents related to John W. Francis's financial claims on N-YHS and the report of the committee established to resolve these. Includes the report of the committee assigned to investigate the conduct of William Ducachet at meetings.
  - Official Papers. 1824-1826 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Official Papers. 1827 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Official Papers. 1828 (1 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 4)